I had a question
well actually I had two
um so the first one is
what is mindfulness of the body
again so like I don't know anything
about the Buddhism I heard about it
heard about
Buddha saying you know mindfulness to
the body
is the weight Enlightenment pretty much
so how'd you do it
or not do it what do you do in order to
practice mindfulness of the body
first thing restraint
embody action
so if somebody does
keep the precepts
restrain the body actions that would
otherwise be rooted in greeter version
distraction how do you do the actual mindfulness
how do you do the actual mindfulness
then
uh-huh what is that
how would you describe it
like in your own terms how do you
describe it yourself basically see in
the body as present no matter
no matter what I do
says well no matter whether I want or
not and whatever I do or can do is or
and whatever I do or can do is or
account with the body being there
beforehand so to see like the bodies
whatever I can engage in the body is
there or or has to be there for any kind
of engagement right so then
would you say that the uh mindfulness of
the body the practice practicing
mindfulness of the body
begins with the um well correct
information as to what the practice is
and what to look for
what could you just do the mindfulness
of the body
no I think there needs to be some
idea I got some idea some view some
knowledge yes
of
well of the right kind
no definitely yeah so it's
what you just described all kind of
comes from the knowledge of what to look
for and the body is already there you're
burning there all that
so it's these
knowledges the context
the context
that's how you begin the mountains of
the body
that's how you can ask the right
questions they would then establish the mind in
they would then establish the mind in
that corrected reflection so it's like
oh what is my body posture now for
example
you don't need to answer it it's enough
for you to ask it the answer is no
because the body's already there in that
posture that's the point here
and that's it now don't overdo that
because people would anybody can do this
in a way but if you view the precedes
the uh the practice of mindfulness is on
the level of
appending to the body in order for it to
be there means you will overlook
this knowledge that is already there
yeah because it comes before your
attention what comes before your
attention how how
it's um
without attending it
Discerning that's being present but
that's attending it you have to attend
something you know to discern it
hmm so yes it comes before but not as a
so yes it comes before but not as a
matter of fact that we can just State
how it comes before okay sure yeah it
doesn't and it does then depends you
have to attend it just where you put the
emphasis on do you put it on the
knowledge that this body that you're
attending has already been sitting like
that or standing like that enduring like
that or are you putting the emphasis on you
or are you putting the emphasis on you
attending it as sitting like that and so
on and it sounds maybe a small thing but
it's actually a completely different
direction of practice Yeah
so the migrants of the body obviously if
one is Center strain because the sense
those Keeps The Virtue starts with the
knowledge of what the body is and
doesn't matter oh but that doesn't feel
palpable enough yeah that's fine it will
become palpable enough it doesn't feel
palpable enough because the threshold of
what you can palpate is on the level of
what I can attend and feel and sensate
and so on
but all of that
all of this particular specific ways of
attending to your body are possible
because the body is already there
so the knowledge of the body already
there enduring regardless of how you
attend it and how you feel about it
is how you established the mindfulness
of the body
and that's why
you establish their mindfulness to the
extent necessary
the final knowledge will be the
dispassion will be the result of it
because nothing can then prevent that
order no matter where your attention goes
no matter where your attention goes
beautiful object
ugly object you know usually provoking a
blast or aversion yeah that peripheral
knowledge of the body during the Dead
image enduring palpable image now
indirect so to speak cannot be forgotten
cannot be stepped outside of cannot be
put second anymore
and then there is no no basis
upon which lust can arise
exactly because for Action that's rooted
in Great River and delusion this has to
be forgotten incense or ignored exactly
and By ignoring it you put the habit of
the wrong order first
and then
you know than any attempt at the
mindfulness through like regaining it
through the direct mindfulness of the
body through like a direct attending and
reminding yourself that you're already
here and here and now and all where else
can you be
all of those attempts would be basically
just rooted in again trying to get rid
of the now discomfort
through your attending and replacing it
with something more comfortable
but a way to get rid of it is to stop
acting out of it and then to recognize
that which is necessary basis for
Comfort or discomfort that you your mind
might be exposed to and that necessary
basis is this physical body there
and that can never be directly attended
it can be known as such
and we go back onto the send spaces that
we discussed before
so
anything to add on this before I go
because you speak about knowing it
and that's something I think that one
could easily Overlook the difference
between knowing something and let's say
perceiving something
and that's even
that's even
in a way something that I would say you
could use
as a way to kind of access the right
type of
um
discernment of the body as such as in
what do I actually know not only what do
I normally see obviously perceive or
something what do I know in the sense
that you know even if
like I as in the entire everybody else
around here could tell me you know no
you're you're standing up
you're standing outside there
and I would still have to know that I'm
sitting that the body is sitting
but it's not only on the level of I
don't know I think I think I'm I'm here
and everybody else says otherwise it's
something I can't it's nothing to do
with what I think or what I prefer or
whether I want to yeah
the significance is in the fact that it
precedes me like so that the that it's
like inescapable that okay yeah I can um
be seated
seated standing walking lying down
I can't not be any of those things that
is it's so so so it's it's this
understanding that
um
this inescapability of being in a
posture that that is the emphasis
because that will be what our brute
agreed hatred and delusion that is the
the that is where this sort of
significance is evoked in that
understanding is not in this I'm sitting
I'm standing
it's not about the specific yeah
specific thing or the well that's really
that's exactly what you just said I was
going to say that so that's important
bit like you can recollect the knowledge
of your body posture I am sitting but
then you can overdo it yeah overattended
so when but that doesn't feel enough
this knowledge that this body is seated
in the background there of whatever I'm
occupied with that doesn't feel as I
said palpable enough so what do you do
then oh let me be mindful and body sweep
this seating body is like oh so you're
putting your attention on the specific
parts of the body first while the
knowledge of the body being there a
necessary basis for specific attentions
you put that second because you
prioritize your craving your lack of
satisfaction and so on and the body
sweeping and everything is what I am
doing so I'm putting so it's kind of
again coming out of that soon tend to
control however subtle so the point is
then to refrain from what we're doing it
as well so don't underdo it I completely
be unaware of your posture but don't
overdo it either it's not better more is
not always better and that's like
playing the strings dilute instrument
the Buddha was talking about it can be
too tight and the sound one one it will
be horrible can be too loose horrible so
you have to get it right and it does
come to that okay so
to some extent I have to attend I attend
to the knowledge I tend to the question
I tend to revoking recollecting that
body didn't use there but now do I
refrain from getting into the specifics
of my attention because it just feels
like I need to do it have it more solid
for me to to to kind of be mindful of it
and then that becomes like what we shoot
in the mark So then you won't be able to
see the body as the necessary basis that
you're confined within some posture at
any given time it will become an
abstraction then you're trying to paste
through your attending to the sensations
and then interpreting and each and
everything else through what you
attended to as a secondary kind of
afterthought um and that's that's just taking away
um and that's that's just taking away
from that middle way
which is a way of
kind of peripheral recognition of what's
there but not not overly
uh attended to like a better word I
suppose and with this analogy of this
string like the music or the
The Sweet Spot I don't know it is
um is dispassion or coming out of great
hatred in delusion that that yeah not as
an abstract idea it is the so the more
familiar you become with the right tune
uh the easier will be to reestablish it
if you lose it and protect it once you
establish it up until that's the only
tune you have and that's when you go
beyond tuning I you don't even need the
Right View anymore as an arrowhead goes
beyond the views
and then all you have is the basis of
this passion cooling down uh
unperversion and that's nibana
and that's nibana
that is also the yeah the characteristic
of
thus uh the right tune or as you put it
the fact that it really doesn't depend
on any
concept or set of ideas or something as
in for example you can like wake up in
the middle of the night and go oh all of
these Concepts and all this dumb and
makes no difference
and be completely in doubt about
everything but then you still find you
have to breathe in like yeah you can't
it's not it's Relentless you cannot
escapists that's and there's something
to recognize in that but you can't get
rid of it you cannot have it
all you can do is stop resisting the
that what you said before the patiga of
it the resistance step
the natural discomfort of it stop
resisting that you will stop
maintaining the basis for wanting
centrality and you will stop maintaining
the basis for uh not wanting pain either
trying to avoid what's unavoidable
the the body that's already there
so for as long as you relate to it with
a degree of passion to that extent again
you will be determined to buy it
so it does come down to learning how to
find that so recognize that you cannot
not attend things
but learn how to attend without losing
the sight
of the context of the background on the
peripheral which is what the only series
which is all discuss before
so um
so since we mentioned the right tune
how'd you then get the right View
how a person
who keeps the veneer or precepts
keeps the veneer or precepts
cards to send those
has the information such as listens in
you know listen to The Talks
practices mindfulness
the best they can in the sense of you
know they don't try to avoid things
through meditation technique
they don't mystify it either how can
they develop the Right View what
what to do how to develop what I view
well I suppose the first thing is to
acknowledge that one doesn't have the
right of you so one is funds funds finds
it runs off in this position of
ignorance that is beginning this so so
to think
that I can somehow imagine the right
view from my current position of
ignorance is is a yeah like a full start
you're undermining your ability to
develop the Right View so then to
recognize that you don't have the right
View into like
even more importantly
recognize that if you don't have the
right View
um
nothing you do
but takes but takes in the Right View
and so it's top to bottom you're
enclosed within your wrong View and
needs to be taken and that therefore
there is some kind of contradiction uh
I mean present in my experience now that
there is some kind of yeah with my
thoughts or my experience that there is
um
yeah some there is a lack of
understanding yeah yeah well that that's
kind of
if you admit that you don't have the
right view yeah then yeah so there is
lack of understanding that what I was
trying to say is that that it's
important to really admit that you don't
have the right view top to bottom
because if you are if you leave that
kind of ambiguous it's okay I don't have
the review you could still cultivate the
attitude as if I don't have the right
view but the stuff I'm doing surely must
be partaking to drive you and getting me
closer to it you don't know even that
you don't know if it's taking you closer
or further away from it because that's
the whole point of not having the right
view means not having the right
reference in other words you can't trust
what you're doing
even if it feels good or right fine
uh don't use the criteria of how it
feels for whether it's right or wrong use the
for whether it's right or wrong use the
information that you're gathering on how
you know what drive you is supposed to
be whether you're supposed to be
resulting but the practice along the
right line should be resulting in not
how it feels but whether it's you know
increasing the last or decreasing it
increasing aversion or decreasing it
are you able to suffer when amid
suffering as much as before or amidst
the stuff they used to make you suffer a
lot you're not as overwhelmed
yeah I was gonna say like you also
make that as a
okay I don't have the right view I don't
uh I must sort of
doubt everything
um
but there has to be some criteria that
you can even verify within your own
experience as having the wrong view to
see this means I have the wrong view
like the reason that's why I can suffer
that and that's therefore like a direct
criteria even to to be able to see
that's not depending on what anybody
else tells you or what any you know what
you hear in the videos or from anywhere
that this correct criteria means that
okay there is there is wrong view there
which also means then you have to yeah
admit that you suffer it's like
recognize when you when you are affected
by them and what uh
what is a necessary basis for people
being able to honestly transparently
authentically admit
did they suffer and they are within
suffering which is kind of a
prerequisite to be able to then relate
to the practice of the Right View
correctly so what is the prerequisite
that kind of what's a necessary basis
for people to be able to admit that
correctly because people might admit
that but still kind of move on as in
yeah but see what I'm doing is is help
and I find this helpful I find this
calming I found all this what all those
things have in common if you haven't
admitted truly
exact management so you have to give up
the management of suffering so wanting
to change acting out of it wanting to
change thinking you can deal with it you
need to fully feel enclosed within the
existing dose of any kind without giving
into okay I'll deal with this that's the
prerequisite for then seeing the craving
as the presently enduring basis for the
present enduring suffering
for as long as you're still holding on a
thread of I can do this this this this I
can calm nostrils sensation this when
it's like this for example it's a soup I
look at Super when it's super all of
these managements are still the reason
why you won't have that idea because
you're not giving up you're dealing with
the pain
so in other words you you're not
uprooting it so in a sense more
specifically one needs to admit that he
doesn't know why he suffers
yes one needs to admit then he doesn't
know why he suffers and then one needs
to restrain himself from managing the
suffering because that's a habit it's
not anymore even on the level of why I
do this it's more like I just do this
and then the Dharma the practice the
talks the sutras became the extension of
your management
so people usually manage suffering
through distraction sensuality acting
out of ill will as they would have said
you know does not know any other escape
from the arteries and painful feeling
other than seeking pleasure in sense
objects uh now somebody's okay that's bad I'll
uh now somebody's okay that's bad I'll
practice meditation and spirituality and
the Dharma and the suitors but if they
do it with the same attitude
so they turn to it to get rid of the
pain to manage the pain
and that won't be the dumb even if it's
all they do is stuff that's what they
say because they're doing it on the base
of their version on the base of the
resistance on the basis of their craving
so then a person can say okay so I was
given in centrality now I'm just sort of
managing the suffering I need to really
refrain myself
from giving into pressure to manage
explain psychologize practice out calm
through my meditation whatever else off
there isn't pressure in my mind
I need to learn how to endure it without
craving against it
and when the craving against diseases
the pain of it ceases while the thing
Still Remains so look amid suffering
amidst the same thing that pressures you
the suffering has ceased because the
craving against it has ceased not the
thing it's still there so it's like oh I
got rid of it I got rid of the problem
of craving
you don't need to get rid of the things
you never did
including your own thoughts
Heaven audition
just to back up slightly the when you
were talking about the
needing to restrain any kind of
management I think part of being able to even you
I think part of being able to even you
know to do that is also even just to you
really need to take responsibility for
the management that you are doing in the
sense that you can do it because you
think so and so told you that it was the
right way or you read it there you need
to
really know this you're the one doing it
and you are fully responsible for any
view about the practice of dhamma that
you are holding as in regardless of
where it comes from or on what basis you
hold it there's no
particular reason to hold any view about
what the dhamma is or what the practice
is you're choosing to do it so only by
taking responsibility for it fully can
you then
you know see that oh I'm doing this out
of craving or I'm doing it just because
I'm doing it so therefore you can
restrain yourself but if you're not
taking responsibility for that from the
beginning this is going to perpetuate
itself yeah your management attempts and
avoidance and stuff yeah there's no way
to to restrain it properly or to even
realize that you're doing it in order to
restrain us
um yeah and that can be like on the
basis of
faith on the basis of
what you interpret the text what you
whatever but but you have to realize
that you're the one having the faith
you're the one interpreting the text
you're the one there's no particular
there's nothing that makes you do it
yeah so practically then
how do you
or if somebody can think of some
examples how do you not how do you refrain from
how do you not how do you refrain from
management
or what happens if you reframe for
management say
s say you see something
that would be like last provoking or
would be like last provoking or
provoking agreed
and then you you didn't act out of it
obviously you refuse to look so you
restrain your senses and now there's
that pressure of
so what do you do then
continue to not act out of it
as in continued to not actually hmm
but so how long
does it work
nothing else
so just not act out of it
can you do anything no
can you go and see somewhere else
read a book
not out of the on the basis of trying to
distract yourself from us
read a book but can you go and sit
somewhere else
save that thing is not still nearby
is it okay if I'm just going to another
room see
see
it depends what the question is based on
can I can I do this or can I do that is
is like all anybody would be asking
those kind of questions from is because
I feel like I need to do something yeah
so you start like that you will you will
be craving against it no doubt but how
far can you go
how far can you allow yourself to go
So you you're not trying to like yeah
precious unpleasant and craving against
this already there because you're
suffering obviously so you cannot just
not do that eventually you can
so now
I'm trying to just
clarify or talk about what is the
Practical extent of what I can do when I
can't pleasure that I'm affected
mistakenly through my wrong views
through my craving
can I go to another room or to another
place um
can I then read something can I then go
to sleep can I go for a walk can I what
what can I do to what extent can I do
stuff I would say yes as long as what's not to
I would say yes as long as what's not to
what
oh some of it
well none of it some of it let's switch
part
if that site is still present you could
move to another room where that site is
not present if that is not done like we
said that's trying to manage the problem
no no but it is it is like you you just
can't handle it yeah is it okay to go to
another room or to another place if you
can't handle the site that are
frequently present yes
can you want to come there
can you read a book or meditate watch
your nostrils feel the sensations to
calm down can you do any can you do that
no not with the nothing with that
intention so why the first one yes why
the second one no
why can't you go to another room because
you're acting on craving but why can't
you just watch your nostrils and calm
down because you're like that okay
what's the difference between the two
I would say the first like if something
is overwhelming to the point where you
eat might make you act out of it
it's better to remove yourself and then
and as I think about it and the second
one is basically acting out of it already
is basically acting out of it already
exactly to the first one has the
imminent danger of losing the sense
restraint like physically
like physically
the second one doesn't
so there's no more danger of you acting
towards or going after or staring or
looking again at the sign to provoking
of lust when you're in your room now you
just don't want to Bear the discomfort
of it so you're watching nostrils to
come read a book or go to sleep or chant
or whatever you do
see now that's what we're doing it
because there is no monument in danger
yeah so when there is imminent danger
avoid it
he has situated in craving but at least
you want like undermine yourself to a
significant degree
like lose the physical restraint verbal
restraint and so on
but now when you're in your room you are
safe there from the imminent danger so
to speak
okay now if you do more it's gonna just
perpetuate management for the sake of it
so that's how you know where to draw a
line so am I here right here like if if I
so am I here right here like if if I
just for a second and my eyes lost the
restraint no there is nothing to look here
no there is nothing to look here
okay so now the pain of it has to be
endured on the level of the mind that
pressure as you said initially for as long as it
as you said initially for as long as it
takes that's kind of the point
and initially it might take quite long
same thing same thing can last for four
or five days just be on your mind same
thing and you don't care in a sense like
for as long as it lasts you're gonna
endure it that's the point
because sometimes people feel like okay
well I'll do this for a week now it's
time to no
no
it's never time to step into the domain
that doesn't belong to you
because the moment you do you're back
into Mara's domain models control
okay this is gonna last forever yeah
domain forever that's the whole point
and there was never a problem
so the problem is that you're just
pressure to to grab hook onto the bait
because you can't bear the presence of
it the the the pressure of it
so if there is the imminent danger to
losing the sense restraint compromising
virtual body speech
physically right here then yes of course
avoid that
wisely avoid it
but if there isn't one
then you have to endure it
because otherwise it's just going to be
self-perpetuating management to try to
keep and basically fueling your craving
because of which you suffer and you're
trying to manage
you don't manage things or you don't
need to manage things because they
bother you you manage things because you
crave against them and your management
against them is another form of craving
so
your management will just result in more
need for management
and same like for being you know they
get ill or something
is pressure in my mind but do I go to
see the doctor that's acting out of
craving yes it is
but is it against the precepts no
if you're cured can you then practice
better yeah if you don't kill yourself
could you die yeah
so then go to the doctor and kind of
craving take responsibility for that
because you know compromising sense
restraining precepts yes on the mental
level you gave in just so that then you
can practice further
but that doesn't mean now that when
there is no illness no imminent danger
or pressure or threat to your sensory
strange you're sitting on your room and
any discomfort you still feel justified
in managing mentally no no that's all
doing it so it's like certain things
the Buddha says should be wisely avoided
like the Wild dog an elephant charcoal
pit don't just overly out of craving if
I turn away from a wild elephant they
will be rooted in craving from attached
to my life
so then I'll just go and let the
elephant kill me was like yeah but you
are still factually not enlightened so
you're gonna die and lose the
opportunity of practice so use some
common sense
basically avoid the elephant admit the
chapter of craving and weakness and then
practice before the next elephant comes
before the next illness comes before the
next overwhelming side
soundsmiletase.com
so the criteria of
um basically practice is the um criteria
for like action so let's say I have a
duty um I impose on me by the community that
um I impose on me by the community that
I live in um
um
yeah I could just not not do it or
refuse to do it but that would be
um I mean like this example of going to
the doctor you go there
to cure your disease so you can practice
you you you yeah it's less hassle to
fulfill your duty yeah yeah so so you
can practice but there is also a line
now see where the uh how about their
Duty goes exactly like somebody can say
okay just fine to go to a doctor
and then just adopt a view then whenever
something bothers you you're Justified
to go to a doctor yeah and equally
somebody says also I must perform a duty
well yeah but it depends on the duties
as well so that requires decide do you
live in the community
where duties imposed on you
are of a more or less practical kind of
necessity or are they just random sort
of decisions by random people they have
nothing to do with any kind of practical
benefit it was just to fulfill time or
ideas or fantasies or whatever else
so is your duty duty revolves around you
know sweeping preparing food preparing
maintenance so then you can live in a
degree of kind of not too uncomfortable
and so on or is it due to revolve around
spending hours or just you know chatting
to people
dusting shrines polishing statues and
stuff that has no practical value
whatsoever yet it's equally time
consuming and requiring company and so
on so there is a there is a different
value to do this as well no it doesn't
mean any Duty should be performed like
is it is performing like in the
successment of Performing Duty towards
your teacher so helping him because he's
teaching you so because you're already a
burden well okay so you take him on as a
burden so just cleaning around each
scooty and so on in return yeah you hear
the Dharma you you get your questions
answered that's a fair deal or you don't
even know what your teacher understands
or not you just took him out of the
institutional value of nisaya that monks
must do and then you're full on 24 7
servant just for the sake of it I was like well
just for the sake of it I was like well
that's not wise isn't it
so just again Common Sense is a
practical need for this
this great Duty or project that
Community does is it is it necessary in
that sense or is it just because
somebody oh I like it I I would like
this can you please solve you spend 10
hours a day doing you know building this
thing for me because I like it
because I would like to have it
because I like all the ideas that
revolve around it or do you like oh no
spend 10 hours fixing the water pipe
because if you don't do it we won't have
water um and then things will get worse in
um and then things will get worse in
other ways get sick and then you'll have
to go to the doctors and so on so like
there is again common sense they would
denominate is this worth doing wasting
my time with because both are yeah
equally can be they can become
distracting and wasting time
uh but yes some of it is necessary to
some extent so but when people accept
the duty at face value
means okay so any context any
discernment of practical necessity need
benefit is gone it's just done because
it's a duty determined by the higher
authority of the tradition Community
senior month or whatever else and that's
certainly not the duty you should be
following
so then you need to change community
or go Mira if you know what you do
or try and talk to community and see if
it can be sort of fixed
because sometimes maybe people lose
perspective but then they can be
reminded and then things can kind of be
restored in a practical order so it's
some duty but again
but if it cannot be restored if the duty
is taken the value of Duty is taken at
the face value you must perform it don't
ask anybody any questions desert
tradition that's the ajan that's our
routine keep doing this for the sake of
doing it there is no discussion there so
you should not live there if you want to
practice for the Right View
so as I said in other talks it's always
just like you again am I doing too much
this just practical questions ask
yourself how much time I spend in
solitude during the day
how much time is spending company how
much of that company time is due to my
own choices and intentions and
volunteering and jumping up for the
opportunity how much is because he was
Duty imposing me unavoidable
and once you clarify how much is a new
how much is nothing you then look at how
much is not on you and whether that's a
problem or not
because sometimes people are always just
so much because they're going around
doing everything nobody asked them to
like there is a degree of personal
responsibility there so you have to
first recognize that
and then see that what when what what's
left oh but it's still like for six seven
oh but it's still like for six seven
hours and to be okay now that's too much
so then you can try and rectify that one
way or the other
because Solitude is necessary you know
we started this how did you get the
right view well
virtue taking the seeing the danger in
the slightest fault slight is acting out
sense restraint so oh it's just it's
just a look it's just a sound nope it's
important to
sustain the value of no I mustn't give
in to this and due to pressures exactly
no don't give in to the management of it
use common sense
manage if you need to go to a doctor or
go to a more quiet place in the room and
so on but not for the sake of avoiding
things to that you know you have to deal
with internally
and then seclusion you need to be
dwelling in seclusion until this the
peripheral the signs of the Mind become
apparent where the mind is the State of
Mind enduring on its own for what it is
because without being alone
that won't be seen because all you see
is yourself through others and others
through your sense of self whatever way
perversion is there of order
but in solitude that gets unpivoted
with these basis of gradual training
setup the Solitude will unpret the you
putting your sense of self first and
then you just see your mind there first
body there first any of these right
perceptions there first
and then you sense yourself and close
within that which means it's not your
own anymore so then your actor becomes
another after still there just now seeing a
after still there just now seeing a
second and ivate second it's not after
anymore it's there which doesn't belong to you
and then we kind of complete the third
Factor they will be abandoned with the
Right View
through this gradual
practices we just described in different
ways but that's exactly what we describe
it
could again just
slightly even just because that very
first thing even that you said
so being restrained and seeing the
danger in the slightest faults
because even that for example you should
not necessarily take for granted from
the beginning what you think a slightest
fault is as in you know somebody might
say okay
yeah I know I I know this
these precepts and so on and supposed to
be
content with that that's not enough for
me I also need to do these odd various
other kind of rules or whatever in order
to feel guilty or something yeah I think
that's so you will have you will take
you everybody will start with
okay everything is a fault and so on you
don't necessarily know so common sense
against uh danger in the slightest fault
means the fault in regard to the
precepts so the police that says you know don't
so the police that says you know don't
lie okay so slightest fault regarding
the principle of lying not telling the
truth I should avoid don't steal don't
kill eight precepts don't eat in the
afternoon and so on okay so the
slightest fault around that but of
course the mind will then make fault out
of things that are not necessarily fault
so try to invent its own rules but
that's when you're like okay so but why
am I doing this now
so you're going to have the pain of
precepts the restraint the pain that's
revealed and account of it
and then exactly you can then double
down on precepts and rules and imposing
more observances and stuff that you do
because you want to manage the painter
there isn't it oh see
says don't eat in the afternoon and
this might be allowable maybe it isn't I
hate it I'm doubtful now
then you kind of find out that actually
was all right in certain instances you
can have certain types of food even as
albino allows
but the doubt the pain of it the guilt
is still there so what do you do now
well if you were honest transparent if
you're as I said covering all the bases
such as okay this is now
and I'm not sorry an Arisen pressure
that's uncomfortable
that but there is no threat I'm not
eating food now there is no food there
is no temperature there is none of that
yet I'm trying to get rid of it
so I'm giving it to the management
and usually what people do when they
don't want to bear that doubt the
discomfort of it okay so it doesn't
matter that it's allowable
in certain cases the Buddha himself
allowed have juice or something if if
there is a if there is a physical need
for it there's illness and so on no I
will never I will never walk near the
fridge again as I keep a word is now
that decision determination oh it's
rooted to you because you want to
prevent the pressure from arising which
means you still hold the view that the
pressure and the pain was on the level
of the food and your senses and it
wasn't and you're already pressured there and
and you're already pressured there and
you're already depression now you're
going to be twice as pressured because
now you you expanded the basis that you
must avoid there was never the problem
to begin with
so yeah that's still about the Panama in
the nutshell when people take on The
Virtue Duty and then
starts including everything and nothing
all for the sake of not even allowing
doubt and uncomfortable State of Mind to
arise on the level of the mind it's like
no no the precepts are about the
physical Behavior verbal Behavior means
it's supposed to arise on the level of
the Mind the pressure the doubt
you know what you're not gonna do so now
you need to understand this on the level
of the mind but no no I'll just do more
I'll just introduce
three times more rules and create new
rules and new way you know the way we
walk and talk and turn around everything
just so that I can micromanage
preemptively these states but then you basically as I
these states but then you basically as I
said you just increased the number of
things now that can cause the same doubt
because initially we just don't need
solid food stay for food in the
afternoon but now it's I walk near the
fridge but I decided I'll never do it it
was a rule that I broke now I feel
guilty I feel doubtful why did I do it
how thick is this juice yeah yeah is it
so now you you again you you go down the
rabbit hole and it's endless and that's
exactly when you become very
neurotic and divorce from reality
whereby precepts and sensory was
initially supposed to create these
states of mind and then you enduring
them rightly you get to see where the
problem is but you never took
responsibility for it and you think
precepts that this was just supposed to
prevent all these things from arising
and that's like when everything becomes
an issue then like it's not enough for
me anymore to double down and create new
rules I need to do for all of you
because you're not doing these little
observances that I do well see my mind
is not full of Doubt because it means I
don't have to do them
so now that's a problem I'm going to
make an issue and try and get you to do
it and you to do it and you to do it why
oh well
because remember what you said the other
day that creating all these boundaries
so that you don't get affected makes you
more exposed to the boundaries and more
exposed and more expensive
yeah you're trying to protect yourself
oh yeah no you said that yeah
well I said it well I said it but you
put it in different words you put
yourself at the front line Yeah by
trying to create a buffer zone so you're
not affected you under being there with
you know maintaining the buffers on so
even more things affect you
but in reality the vinaya counting the
precepts gardening with the Senators and
if you take responsibility for the
mental states that arise on account of
it and not try to manage them and get
rid of them that is the buffer zone
that's where the confidence will come
from because you know what you're not doing
because you know what you're not doing
you know what you will not do everything
else doesn't matter oh that's actually
quite easy
and that's exactly what it would have
said when so like you know there were a
few rules but some monks find them too
many already
and he said well not to go there's just
too much all these I can't keep it in my
mind you say okay we'll keep these three
don't do anything that's rooted in
create a version delusion yeah okay
that's clear enough
so stay on that first for most people
like you know vastly kind of ambiguous
level of don't do anything
better tell me something more specific
but for him it was more more than enough
specific specific enough
great diversion delusion if that's
present I won't do it yeah but that was
because he was a noble disciple so he
yeah so he saw that directly for him
exactly yeah so if you're not as I said
you need some definition and that's what
it would have did give the definition of
weight preset
false obvious Common Sense fault within
that you know like oh well see
technically I'm not lying but
habitually but you can't not quite doing
it so that you can say you didn't break
the prison so that would constitute a
fault you can say okay so seeing the
danger in the slightest form it's a
slight fault it's not fully against the
presets but is it the fault is it a bit
against yes so it's a bit against it so
it's a bit of a fault slightest fault so
keeping the precepts in the danger in
the slightest fault in regard to the
precepts guard just sends those that's
it moderate in eating of course sure
solitude and within that
and within that
your need your habit no matter how
deeply embedded it was before to manage
that is a mental state can be sort of
dampened and eventually seen through and
then you recognize where the problem was
your own craving not the mental States
so when we're not acting
in this
managing way he's already putting into
question the wrong view also to say and the
the wrong view also to say and the
beliefs of who are well it says not
feeding them further yeah yeah
definitely definitely
yeah because that's you know as University
because that's you know as University
said in one of I don't know the letters
he says the whole point of the Dharma is
not to help you manage
you know unpleasant sight sound smell
taste touches memories and help you deal
with it no it's supposed to uproot your
entire experience as a whole all of it
nothing there's no oh it helps me with
this and it's helpful at this time or at
this occasion or no no it doesn't deal
with the specific experiences it
approves experience
Baba has ceased existence has ceased for
a mind that's that's completely free
from Passion and enlightened
so if existence has ceased nothing more
specific within that existence can
bother you can be an issue but if you
refuse to give up the view of just
justification to deal with things that
bother you
internally externally maybe I'm
restrained but I'm a managing a place of
concentration and then there's something
I have more observances I have little
routines yeah that's still not the Dharma because
yeah that's still not the Dharma because
you're not you're not because you need
to give up that view of management
in order to basically force yourself to
look at it on the level of existence
and that's the level where things can be
uprooted